Draper Corporation Photographs 6612 P
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Draper Corporation Photographs
1882-1920
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Draper Corporation
6612 P
10.11 cubic feet
9.6 linear ft.
Gelatin silver print, photographs.
Photographs of the Draper Corporations buildings, executives, employees, and the machinery built by the company, as well as photographs of Hopedale, Massachusetts.
10085763
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
R. Miles, November 02, 2017
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, December 22, 2017
Biographical / Historical
The Draper Corporation was once the largest maker of power looms for the textile industry in the United States. It operated in Hopedale, Massachusetts for more than 130 years.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists mostly of prints from the glass plate negatives in collection 6612 GPN: Draper Corporation Glass Plate Negatives. Collection 6612 GPN consists of two series: Series A, 5 inch by 7 inch glass plate negatives, approximately 1,500; and Series B, 8 inch by 10 inch glass plate negatives, approximately 2,000.
Many of the photographs in Series A depict company outings, or "Field Days." These events were most likely organized by the Draper Company and may have consisted entirely of Draper Company employees. Founders of the Draper Company, brothers George and Ebenezer Draper were responsible for creating an integrated, planned community with innovative employee housing and recreational spaces, in addition to employment.
Series B consists largely of machinery built by the Draper Company. Also included are photographs of the company plant, employee housing, recreational facilities, and the surrounding area.
All negatives in collection 6612 GPN have been printed and included in this collection. Of the roughly 3,500 negatives 513 have been described at the individual level. Those descriptions are available in the container lists for both this collection and collection 6612 GPN.
In addition to the photographs from 6612 GPN, other photographs of Draper Corporation machinery, buildings, employees, and executives are included in this collection.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 6612 G: Draper Corporation Graphics 6612 GPN: Draper Corporation Glass Plate Negatives 6612 PUBS: Draper Corporation Publications
Battery (Loom); Construction--Textile mill; Factories; Foundries; Industrial chimneys; Industrial housing; Male employees; Looms; Office buildings; Screw machines, Automatic; Shuttles (Textile machinery); Spindles (Textile machinery); Textile factories; Textile machinery; Textile machinery industry; Textile machinery industry--Employees--Dwellings--Hopedale (Mass.); Textile machinery industry-- Employees--Dwellings--Milford (Mass.); Textile manufacturers; Textile workers; Twisting machines (Textile machinery); Weaving; Woodshops; World War, 1914-1918; World War, 1939-1945; Hopedale (Mass.); Milford (Mass.); Austin, Charles F.; Ballou, Adin; Bancroft, Joseph B.; Burgess, George M.; Clarke, George R.; Clarke, George T.; Day, Charles M.; Draper, Eben S.; Draper, George.; Draper, Hannah.; Draper, William F.; Dutcher, Warren W.; Hatch, G. N.; Hatch, G. N., Dr.; Northrup, James Henry.; Osgood, Edward Louis.; Osgood, Hannah Twing Draper.; Story, Waldo.; Swasey, Fred.; Walker, Charles Howard, 1857-1936; A.A. Westcott & Sons.; Atlantic Cotton Mills.; Bancroft Memorial Library.; C.F. Roper & Co.; Draper Company.; Draper Corporation.; Henry L. Patrick Store; Hopedale Elastic Fabric Company.; Hopedale House; Hopedale Park; Hopedale Pond; Kilburn, Lincoln & Company; Mt. Vernon-Woodberry Mills; Osgood House; Peabody & Stearns (Boston, Mass.); Queen City Cotton Company (Burlington, Vt.); Whitin Machine Works (Whitinsville, Mass.)
10085763
- Contact prints from glass plate negatives, Series A:1-20: box no. 6 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Contact prints from glass plate negatives, Series A:21-40: box no. 7 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 22: Close-up view of battery on Draper Company loom, Model E, with duflex (?) harness, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Scope and Contents
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.A22. 1894-1900. Image depicts a close-up view of the battery on a Draper Company Model E loom with a duplex (?) harness. A battery is a mechanism found on single box automatic looms. The battery holds a plentiful supply of filling bobbins and transfers them, one at a time, to the shuttle as the need arises. The Draper Company, located in Hopedale, Massachusetts, manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. See Item 27, in this folder, for a view of the entire loom. 25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 27: Draper Co. loom, Model E, with duflex (?) harness, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.A27. 1894-1900. Image depicts a Draper Company Model E loom with a duplex (?) harness. The loom has been photographed against a temporary background set up within an unknown mill. According to a 1900 catalog published by Draper, the E model loom had a regular pattern for prints and sheetings. The Draper Company, located in Hopedale, Massachusetts, manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. See Item 22, in this folder, for a close-up view of the battery on this loom. 25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 31: Loom: D Model LH, Draper Company, 1898; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.A31. Image depicts a view of a Draper Company D Model LH Loom, photographed against a sheet, most likely within an unknown mill. This model appears very similar to the D Model loom seen in Box 1, Folder 3, Item 73, but is not exactly the same. A notation on the back of the print reads: "Draper Loom - D Model LH Mar 1898." The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 37: Loom: A Model, Draper Company, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.A37. 1894-1900. Image depicts a view of a Draper Company A Model loom, photographed against a sheet, most likely within an unknown mill. The loom has a battery on the right-hand side. The Model A loom was also called the 1894 pattern, and was obsolete by 1900. The Model A loom had a shorter lay and shuttle box than was used by Draper by 1900, had a Mason take-up and plain rocker motions. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 38: Loom: D Model (rear view), Draper Company, 1898; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.A38. 1898? Image depicts the rear view of a D-model loom set up on a white cloth on the floor, with a curtain draped behind it for photography purposes, most likely within an unknown mill. The D-model loom was considered a heavy standard loom. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. See Box 1, Folder 3, Item 73 for the front view of this loom, which was dated from 1898. 25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 39: Draper Company Loom - E Model, 1900, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.A39. Image depicts a view of an E-model loom from 1900, set up on a white cloth on the floor, with a curtain draped behind it for photography purposes, most likely within an unknown mill. The loom has a battery on the right-hand side. Draper Company is incised on the frame. Very similar (if not identical) to the loom seen in Item 27, in this folder. The E-model loom had a regular pattern for prints and sheetings. The Draper Company, located in Hopedale, Massachusetts, manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 25 x 20.25 cm.
- Contact prints from glass plate negatives, Series A:41-80: box no. 8-9, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Item 44: Drafting Room, October 1900, Draper Company, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.A44. October 1900. Image depicts a view of the Drafting Room at the Draper Company. Individual drafting tables on the right appear to be separated by sheets. The right side of the room appears to be flooded with light. Windows are visible in the rear. More drafting tables with cloth (?) spread out on them are in the foreground. The calendar on the rear wall reads October 1900. This view is a different angle from that seen in Box 1, Folder 5, Item 999, Box 1, Folder 6, Item 1040 and Box 1, Folder 7, Item 1051. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 46: Loom: E Model, Draper Company, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.A46. 1894-1900. Image depicts a view of an E-model loom with one battery on the right side. "Hopedale Draper Company Massachusetts" incised on frame. The E model loom was for a regular pattern for prints and sheetings. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 47: Draper Company Loom frame (D Model), 1898; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.A47. Image depicts a view of a D-model loom frame, seen here without any interior parts attached. A notation on the back of the print reads: "Loom frame (D Model) May 1898." The Draper Company, located in Hopedale, Massachusetts, manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 48: F Model Loom, Draper Company, 1900; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.A48. Image depicts a view of an F-model loom seen here from the rear. The F model loom was designed for an extra heavy pattern for goods 72 inches and wider. A notation on the back of the print reads: "Loom - F Model Feb 15, 1900." See Item 55, in this folder, for a close-up view of an F model loom from the end showing the picker stick. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 49: Dobby Loom, D Model, Draper Company, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.A49. 1894-1900. Image depicts a view of a D-model dobby loom, photographed against a sheet, probably in an unknown mill. The battery is on the right with a long box for the bobbins. A dobby loom is a loom equipped with a dobby and capable of weaving small figures. The dobby is a mechanism attached to a loom for controlling the operation of the harnesses. Dobbies are made so that they can operate up to 25 harnesses and by this means figured cloths can be woven. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 50: C Model Loom with a duplex harness, Draper Company, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.A50. 1894-1900. Image depicts a view of a C-model loom with a duplex harness, photographed against a sheet, probably in an unknown mill. The battery is on the right-hand side, although there appears to be no box for the bobbins. The harness is the frame containing the heddles through which the warp threads are drawn prior to weaving. By lifting or lowering the harnesses in the loom the shed is formed. The shed is the opening formed when some warp threads are raised by their harnesses while others are left down. Forming the shed is the first action in weaving, and it is through the shed that the shuttle passes in inserting the filling. This loom contains two harnesses. The C model loom was Draper's first heavy pattern loom and was obsolete by 1900. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 52: B Model Loom, Draper Company, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.A52. 1894-1900. Image depicts a view of a B model loom, photographed against a sheet, probably in an unknown mill. The B model loom, also called the 1895 loom, was the Draper standard for prints and other light goods until 1898. The loom was obsolete by 1900. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 25 x 20.25 cm. Copy A.
  - Item 54: D Model Loom with a worm gear take-up motion, Draper Company, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.A54. 1894-1900. Image depicts a view of a D model loom with a worm gear take-up motion, photographed against a sheet, probably in an unknown mill. The take-up motion is a mechanism on a loom for taking up the cloth as it is woven. The speed with which it performs this action determines the number of picks per inch. A worm gear take-up motion is continuous, as opposed to the intermittent motion. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 55: Close-up view of F Model Loom, Draper Company, 1900; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.A55. Image depicts a close-up view of an F-model loom seen from one end, showing the picker stick. (The picker stick, by delivering a sharp blow to the shuttle, causes the shuttle to be thrown from one shuttle box, across the race plate, into the opposite shuttle box.) The F model loom was designed for an extra heavy pattern for goods 72 inches and wider. A notation on the back of the print reads: "F Model Loom Feb 1900." See Item 48, in this folder, for a broader view of an F model loom. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 62: J Model, 20-Harness Dobby Loom, Draper Company, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.A62. 1894-1900. Image depicts a view of a J model dobby loom, with 20 harnesses. A dobby loom is a loom equipped with a dobby and capable of weaving small figures. The dobby is a mechanism attached to a loom for controlling the operation of the harnesses. Dobbies are made so that they can operate up to 25 harnesses and by this means figured cloths can be woven. The harness is the frame containing the heddles through which the warp threads are drawn prior to weaving. By lifting or lowering the harnesses in the loom the shed is formed. The shed is the opening formed when some warp threads are raised by their harnesses while others are left down. Forming the shed is the first action in weaving, and it is through the shed that the shuttle passes in inserting the filling. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 63: Dobby Loom (side view), Draper Company, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.A63. 1894-1900. Image depicts the side view of dobby loom by Draper Company. Possibly the side view of the dobby loom seen in Item 62 and Item 64, in this folder, which is described as a 20-harness J Model, but it is difficult to establish from this angle. Clearly this loom has multiple harnesses on it. A dobby loom is a loom equipped with a dobby and capable of weaving small figures. The dobby is a mechanism attached to a loom for controlling the operation of the harnesses. Dobbies are made so that they can operate up to 25 harnesses and by this means figured cloths can be woven. The harness is the frame containing the heddles through which the warp threads are drawn prior to weaving. By lifting or lowering the harnesses in the loom the shed is formed. The shed is the opening formed when some warp threads are raised by their harnesses while others are left down. Forming the shed is the first action in weaving, and it is through the shed that the shuttle passes in inserting the filling. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 20.25 x 25 cm.
  - Item 64: J Model, 20-Harness Dobby Loom (rear view), Draper Company, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.A64. 1894-1900. Image depicts the rear view of a J model dobby loom, with 20 harnesses, photographed against a sheet, probably in an unknown mill. A dobby loom is a loom equipped with a dobby and capable of weaving small figures. The dobby is a mechanism attached to a loom for controlling the operation of the harnesses. Dobbies are made so that they can operate up to 25 harnesses and by this means figured cloths can be woven. The harness is the frame containing the heddles through which the warp threads are drawn prior to weaving. By lifting or lowering the harnesses in the loom the shed is formed. The shed is the opening formed when some warp threads are raised by their harnesses while others are left down. Forming the shed is the first action in weaving, and it is through the shed that the shuttle passes in inserting the filling. See Item 62, in this folder, for the front view of this loom and Item 63, in this folder, for what is probably the side view of this loom. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 65: Loom: A Model, side view, Draper Company, 1894; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.A65. Image depicts the side view of an A Model loom by Draper Company. The A Model loom was the first loom sent out to various manufacturers by Draper; it had a shorter lay and shuttle box than later used, a Mason take-up, and plain rocker motions. By 1900 it was obsolete. A notation on the back of the print reads: "Loom - Pulley End A Model Dec 22, 1894." The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 66: Loom: A Model, side view showing battery, Draper Company, 1900; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.A66. Image depicts the side view of an A Model loom by Draper Company, this side showing the battery. Photographed against a sheet, probably in an unknown mill. Note the short drop box beneath the battery. The A Model loom was the first loom sent out to various manufacturers by Draper; it had a shorter lay and shuttle box than later used, a Mason take-up, and plain rocker motions. By 1900 it was obsolete. A notation on the back of the print reads: "Loom - A Model Mpv 25, 1900." The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 20.25 x 25 cm.
  - Item 67: B Model Loom, Draper Company, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.A67. 1894-1900. Image depicts a view of a B model loom, photographed against a sheet, probably in an unknown mill. The B model loom, also called the 1895 loom, was the Draper standard for prints and other light goods until 1898. The loom was obsolete by 1900. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 25 x 20.25 cm. Copy B.
  - Item 73: Loom: D Model, Draper Company, 1898; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.A73. Image depicts a D-model loom set up on a white cloth on the floor, with a curtain draped behind it for photography purposes, most likely within an unknown mill. Draper Company is incised on the top crosspiece. A notation on the back of the print reads: "Loom - D Model, Mar 22, 1898." The D- model loom was considered a heavy standard loom. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. See Box 1, Folder 2, Item 38 for what is most likely the rear view of this loom. 25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 74: Loom (sent to Queen City Cotton Company, 1894), Draper Company, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.A74. Image depicts a loom with two batteries. The area has been set off with a sheet to isolate the loom for photography, most likely within an unknown mill. A notation on the back of the print reads: "Loom (first fair, sent to Queen City Cotton Co.), Dec. 22, 1894." The reference to a fair could be a reference to a textile machinery exposition of some sort. The Queen City Cotton Co. was located in Burlington, Vt. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 80: Loom: D Model, Northrup Loom, Draper Company, 1898; black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.A80. Image depicts a D-model Northrup loom set up against a white curtain draped behind it for photography purposes, most likely within an unknown mill. Draper Company is incised on the top crosspiece; "The Northrup Loom" is clearly visible on the front of the loom. A notation on the back of the print reads: "Loom - D Model, Mar, 1898." The D-model loom was considered a heavy standard loom. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms, and specifically Northrup looms. 25 x 20.25 cm.
- Contact prints from glass plate negatives, Series A:81-116, 502: box no. 10-11, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Item 87: Keene drawing-in frame, Draper Company, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.A87. 1894-1900. Image depicts a view of a Keene drawing-in frame manufactured by the Draper Company. Drawing-in is the process of entering the warp ends from the warp beam through the eyes of the correct heddles on the respective harnesses. The warp beam here is on the right; the warp ends are being drawn through the heddles but the angle of the photograph does not show that clearly, since the frame is seen from the side. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 20.25 x 25 cm.
  - Item 89: Close-up view of gears on Speeder, Draper Company, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.A89. 1894-1900]. Image depicts a close-up view of the gears on the end of a speeder, which is a term sometimes used for the third machine in a series of roving frames, or applied to roving frames in general. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. See Item 94, in this folder, for an expanded view of this machine. 20.25 x 25 cm.
  - Item 90: Speeder (rear view), Draper Company, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.A90. 1891-1895. Image depicts the view from the rear of a speeder, which is a term sometimes used for the third machine in a series of roving frames, or applied to roving frames in general. See Item 94, in this folder, for the front view of this machine. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. 25 x 20.25 cm.
  - Item 94: Speeder, Draper Co., black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Printed in 1974 from glass plate negative no.A94. 1891-1895. Image depicts a speeder, which is a term sometimes used for the third machine in a series of roving frames, or applied to roving frames in general. "Draper Company Hopedale Massachusetts" can be seen on the side of the machine. The Draper Company manufactured textile machinery, primarily looms. See Item 90, in this folder, for the rear view of this machine. 25 x 20.25 cm.
- Contact prints from glass plate negatives, Series A:994-1021, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Item 994: Temple Shop, Draper Company, black and white photograph (Box 1, Folder 5)